Introduction
To Our Venerable Brethren the Patriarchs, Primates, Archbishops, Bishops, and other
Ordinaries of Places having Peace and Communion with the Apostolic See.
That the spirit of revolutionary change, which has long been disturbing the nations
of the world, should have passed beyond the sphere of politics and made its
influence felt in the cognate sphere of practical economics is not surprising. The
Therefore, venerable brethren, as on former occasions when it seemed opportune to
refute false teaching, We have addressed you in the interests of the Church and of
the common weal, and have issued letters bearing on political power, human liberty,
In any case we clearly see, and on this there is general agreement, that some
opportune remedy must be found quickly for the misery and wretchedness pressing so
unjustly on the majority of the working class: for the ancient workingmen’s guilds
I. Socialism, a False Remedy
To remedy these wrongs the socialists, working on the poor man’s envy of the rich,
are striving to do away with private property, and contend that individual
possessions should become the common property of all, to be administered by the
It is surely undeniable that, when a man engages in remunerative labor, the
impelling reason and motive of his work is to obtain property, and thereafter to
hold it as his very own. If one man hires out to another his strength or skill, he
What is of far greater moment, however, is the fact that the remedy they propose is
manifestly against justice. For, every man has by nature the right to possess
property as his own. This is one of the chief points of distinction between man and
This becomes still more clearly evident if man’s nature be considered a little more
deeply. For man, fathoming by his faculty of reason matters without number, linking
the future with the present, and being master of his own acts, guides his ways under
The fact that God has given the earth for the use and enjoyment of the whole human
race can in no way be a bar to the owning of private property. For God has granted
the earth to mankind in general, not in the sense that all without distinction can
Here, again, we have further proof that private ownership is in accordance with the
law of nature. Truly, that which is required for the preservation of life, and for
life’s well-being, is produced in great abundance from the soil, but not until man
So strong and convincing are these arguments that it seems amazing that some should
now be setting up anew certain obsolete opinions in opposition to what is here laid
down. They assert that it is right for private persons to have the use of the soil
With reason, then, the common opinion of mankind, little affected by the few
dissentients who have contended for the opposite view, has found in the careful
study of nature, and in the laws of nature, the foundations of the division of
The rights here spoken of, belonging to each individual man, are seen in much
stronger light when considered in relation to man’s social and domestic obligations.
In choosing a state of life, it is indisputable that all are at full liberty to
That right to property, therefore, which has been proved to belong naturally to
individual persons, must in like wise belong to a man in his capacity of head of a
family; nay, that right is all the stronger in proportion as the human person
The contention, then, that the civil government should at its option intrude into
and exercise intimate control over the family and the household is a great and
pernicious error. True, if a family finds itself in exceeding distress, utterly
And in addition to injustice, it is only too evident what an upset and disturbance
there would be in all classes, and to how intolerable and hateful a slavery citizens
would be subjected. The door would be thrown open to envy, to mutual invective, and
II. The Church and the Social Question
We approach the subject with confidence, and in the exercise of the rights which
manifestly appertain to Us, for no practical solution of this question will be found
apart from the intervention of religion and of the Church. It is We who are the
It must be first of all recognized that the condition of things inherent in human
affairs must be borne with, for it is impossible to reduce civil society to one dead
level. Socialists may in that intent do their utmost, but all striving against
In like manner, the other pains and hardships of life will have no end or cessation
on earth; for the consequences of sin are bitter and hard to bear, and they must
accompany man so long as life lasts. To suffer and to endure, therefore, is the lot
The great mistake made in regard to the matter now under consideration is to take up
with the notion that class is naturally hostile to class, and that the wealthy and
the working men are intended by nature to live in mutual conflict. So irrational and
Of these duties, the following bind the proletarian and the worker: fully and
faithfully to perform the work which has been freely and equitably agreed upon;
never to injure the property, nor to outrage the person, of an employer; never to
But the Church, with Jesus Christ as her Master and Guide, aims higher still. She
lays down precepts yet more perfect, and tries to bind class to class in
friendliness and good feeling. The things of earth cannot be understood or valued
Therefore, those whom fortune favors are warned that riches do not bring freedom
from sorrow and are of no avail for eternal happiness, but rather are obstacles;
that the rich should tremble at the threatenings of Jesus Christ — threatenings so
As for those who possess not the gifts of fortune, they are taught by the Church
that in God’s sight poverty is no disgrace, and that there is nothing to be ashamed
of in earning their bread by labor. This is enforced by what we see in Christ
From contemplation of this divine Model, it is more easy to understand that the true
worth and nobility of man lie in his moral qualities, that is, in virtue; that
virtue is, moreover, the common inheritance of men, equally within the reach of high
But, if Christian precepts prevail, the respective classes will not only be united
in the bonds of friendship, but also in those of brotherly love. For they will
understand and feel that all men are children of the same common Father, who is God;
But the Church, not content with pointing out the remedy, also applies it. For the
Church does her utmost to teach and to train men, and to educate them and by the
intermediary of her bishops and clergy diffuses her salutary teachings far and wide.
On this subject we need but recall for one moment the examples recorded in history.
Of these facts there cannot be any shadow of doubt: for instance, that civil society
was renovated in every part by Christian institutions; that in the strength of that
Neither must it be supposed that the solicitude of the Church is so preoccupied with
the spiritual concerns of her children as to neglect their temporal and earthly
interests. Her desire is that the poor, for example, should rise above poverty and
The Church, moreover, intervenes directly in behalf of the poor, by setting on foot
and maintaining many associations which she knows to be efficient for the relief of
poverty. Herein, again, she has always succeeded so well as to have even extorted
Thus, by degrees, came into existence the patrimony which the Church has guarded
with religious care as the inheritance of the poor. Nay, in order to spare them the
shame of begging, the Church has provided aid for the needy. The common Mother of
It cannot, however, be doubted that to attain the purpose we are treating of, not
only the Church, but all human agencies, must concur. All who are concerned in the
matter should be of one mind and according to their ability act together. It is with
III. The Role of the State
By the State we here understand, not the particular form of government prevailing in
this or that nation, but the State as rightly apprehended; that is to say, any
government conformable in its institutions to right reason and natural law, and to
There is another and deeper consideration which must not be lost sight of. As
regards the State, the interests of all, whether high or low, are equal. The members
of the working classes are citizens by nature and by the same right as the rich;
But although all citizens, without exception, can and ought to contribute to that
common good in which individuals share so advantageously to themselves, yet it
should not be supposed that all can contribute in the like way and to the same
We have said that the State must not absorb the individual or the family; both
should be allowed free and untrammeled action so far as is consistent with the
common good and the interest of others. Rulers should, nevertheless, anxiously
Whenever the general interest or any particular class suffers, or is threatened with
harm, which can in no other way be met or prevented, the public authority must step
in to deal with it. Now, it is to the interest of the community, as well as of the
Rights must be religiously respected wherever they exist, and it is the duty of the
public authority to prevent and to punish injury, and to protect every one in the
possession of his own. Still, when there is question of defending the rights of
Here, however, it is expedient to bring under special notice certain matters of
moment. First of all, there is the duty of safeguarding private property by legal
enactment and protection. Most of all it is essential, where the passion of greed is
When work people have recourse to a strike and become voluntarily idle, it is
frequently because the hours of labor are too long, or the work too hard, or because
they consider their wages insufficient. The grave inconvenience of this not uncommon
The working man, too, has interests in which he should be protected by the State;
and first of all, there are the interests of his soul. Life on earth, however good
and desirable in itself, is not the final purpose for which man is created; it is
From this follows the obligation of the cessation from work and labor on Sundays and
certain holy days. The rest from labor is not to be understood as mere giving way to
idleness; much less must it be an occasion for spending money and for vicious
If we turn now to things external and material, the first thing of all to secure is
to save unfortunate working people from the cruelty of men of greed, who use human
beings as mere instruments for money-making. It is neither just nor human so to
IV. The Question of Wages
We now approach a subject of great importance, and one in respect of which, if
extremes are to be avoided, right notions are absolutely necessary. Wages, as we are
told, are regulated by free consent, and therefore the employer, when he pays what
To this kind of argument a fair-minded man will not easily or entirely assent; it is
not complete, for there are important considerations which it leaves out of account
altogether. To labor is to exert oneself for the sake of procuring what is necessary
Let the working man and the employer make free agreements, and in particular let
them agree freely as to the wages; nevertheless, there underlies a dictate of
natural justice more imperious and ancient than any bargain between man and man,
If a workman’s wages be sufficient to enable him comfortably to support himself, his
wife, and his children, he will find it easy, if he be a sensible man, to practice
thrift, and he will not fail, by cutting down expenses, to put by some little
Many excellent results will follow from this; and, first of all, property will
certainly become more equitably divided. For, the result of civil change and
revolution has been to divide cities into two classes separated by a wide chasm. On
V. Workers’ Associations
In the last place, employers and workmen may of themselves effect much, in the
matter We are treating, by means of such associations and organizations as afford
opportune aid to those who are in distress, and which draw the two classes more
The most important of all are workingmen’s unions, for these virtually include all
the rest. History attests what excellent results were brought about by the
artificers’ guilds of olden times. They were the means of affording not only many
The consciousness of his own weakness urges man to call in aid from without. We read
in the pages of holy Writ: “It is better that two should be together than one; for
they have the advantage of their society. If one fall he shall be supported by the
These lesser societies and the larger society differ in many respects, because their
immediate purpose and aim are different. Civil society exists for the common good,
and hence is concerned with the interests of all in general, albeit with individual
There are occasions, doubtless, when it is fitting that the law should intervene to
prevent certain associations, as when men join together for purposes which are
evidently bad, unlawful, or dangerous to the State. In such cases, public authority
And here we are reminded of the confraternities, societies, and religious orders
which have arisen by the Church’s authority and the piety of Christian men. The
annals of every nation down to our own days bear witness to what they have
Associations of every kind, and especially those of working men, are now far more
common than heretofore. As regards many of these there is no need at present to
inquire whence they spring, what are their objects, or what the means they imply.
Those Catholics are worthy of all praise — and they are not a few — who,
understanding what the times require, have striven, by various undertakings and
endeavors, to better the condition of the working class by rightful means. They have
In order that an association may be carried on with unity of purpose and harmony of
action, its administration and government should be firm and wise. All such
societies, being free to exist, have the further right to adopt such rules and
To sum up, then, We may lay it down as a general and lasting law that working men’s
associations should be so organized and governed as to furnish the best and most
suitable means for attaining what is aimed at, that is to say, for helping each
The foundations of the organization being thus laid in religion, We next proceed to
make clear the relations of the members one to another, in order that they may live
together in concord and go forward prosperously and with good results. The offices
Such rules and regulations, if willingly obeyed by all, will sufficiently ensure the
well-being of the less well-to-do; whilst such mutual associations among Catholics
are certain to be productive in no small degree of prosperity to the State. Is it
At the time being, the condition of the working classes is the pressing question of
the hour, and nothing can be of higher interest to all classes of the State than
that it should be rightly and reasonably settled. But it will be easy for Christian
And further great advantage would result from the state of things We are describing;
there would exist so much more ground for hope, and likelihood, even, of recalling
to a sense of their duty those working men who have either given up their faith
We have now laid before you, venerable brethren, both who are the persons and what
are the means whereby this most arduous question must be solved. Every one should
put his hand to the work which falls to his share, and that at once and straightway,
In regard to the Church, her cooperation will never be found lacking, be the time or
the occasion what it may; and she will intervene with all the greater effect in
proportion as her liberty of action is the more unfettered. Let this be carefully
On each of you, venerable brethren, and on your clergy and people, as an earnest of
God’s mercy and a mark of Our affection, we lovingly in the Lord bestow the
apostolic benediction.
Given at St. Peter’s in Rome, the fifteenth day of May, 1891, the fourteenth year of
Our pontificate. — LEO XIII